Haneul Yoo

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

📞 +82-10-5269-2387 | 🖂 haneul.yoo@kaist.ac.kr | 🏕 haneul-yoo.github.io | 🖸 haneul-yoo | **in** haneulyoo | 💆 HaneulYoo13

About _

Haneul Yoo is a Ph.D. candidate advised by Professor Alice Oh in the School of Computing at KAIST. Her research interest primarily lies in the field of natural language processing and machine learning. Her ultimate goal is to bridge the gap of communication among different cultures and languages with the help of large language models (LLMs). In particular, she is dedicated to (1) data-centric and multilingual NLP and (2) LLM-driven education innovation. She has worked on boosting communications of non-native speakers by (1) enhancing the performances of LLMs, especially in low-resource languages, through the release of datasets and benchmarks and (2) assisting their language learning through LLM-driven education innovation.

Education

KAIST Daejeon, Korea

Sep 2022 - CURRENT Ph.D. IN SCHOOL OF COMPUTING

· Advisor: Alice Oh

KAIST Daejeon, Korea M.S. IN SCHOOL OF COMPUTING Sep 2020 - Aug 2022

· Advisor: Alice Oh

Ajou University Suwon, Korea

B.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

Mar 2017 - Aug 2020 B.S. IN DIGITAL MEDIA

• University of Wisconsin - Stout, WI, USA — Semester Abroad Winter 2018

Experience _____

Naver AI Lab Sungnam, Korea

Mar 2024 - May 2024 RESEARCH INTERN

• Development of multilingual LLMs using code-switching corpora

· Advisor: Hwaran Lee

Upstage Remote

DATA MANAGEMENT INTERN Aug 2023 - Feb 2024 · Construction and management of Korean evaluation benchmark for LLMs

· Advisor: Taehwan Oh and Jiyoon Han

Naver Allah Sungnam, Korea

Mar 2023 - Jul 2023

VISITING STUDENT

Construction and management of KoBBQ, Korean bias benchmark for question answering

· Advisor: Hwaran Lee

LAMDA Lab @ Ajou University Suwon, Korea Mar 2020 - Aug 2020

Undergraduage Student Researcher • Study of Deep Learning Model for Bio-signal (EEG) Analysis

Advisor: Jungryul Seo and Kyung-Ah Sohn

KEPCO Research Institute (KEPRI)

Daejeon, Korea RESEARCH INTERN Sep 2019 - Feb 2020

• Development of application services utilizing electric used power data

· Advisor: Moonsuk Choi

Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO) QLD, Australia Jul 2019 - Aug 2019

• Development of Convolutional deep neural network for detecting cattle in images/videos

· Advisor: Brano Kusy

Indielist Suwon, Korea

SOFTWARE ENGINEER & CO-FOUNDER Jul 2018 - Jun 2019

Establishment of an independent music platform and development of iOS application services

Publications ______* denotes equal contributions
INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCES / JOURNALS

RECIPE4U: Student-ChatGPT Dialogue in EFL Writing Education LREC-COLING

Jieun Han*, **Haneul Yoo***, Junho Myung, Minsun Kim, Tak Yeon Lee, So-Yeon Ahn, Alice Oh in press

CLIcK: Evaluation of Cultural and Linguistic Intelligence in Korean

LREC-COLING

Juyoung Suk*, Eunsu Kim*, Philhoon Oh, **Haneul Yoo**, James Throne, Alice Oh in-press

KOBBQ: Korean Bias Benchmark for Question Answering

Jiho Jin*, Jiseon Kim*, Nayeon Lee*, Haneul Yoo*, Alice Oh, Hwaran Lee

in press

Rethinking Annotation: Can Language Learners Contribute?

**ACL Haneul Yoo, Rifki Afina Putri, Changyoon Lee, Youngin Lee, So-Yeon Ahn, Dongyeop Kang, Alice Oh

Jul 2023

Jul 2023

ACL Danguage Learners Contribute?

**ACL Danguage Learners Contribute?*

**AC

Translating Hanja Historical Documents to Understandable Korean and English

Juhee Son*, Jiho Jin*, Haneul Yoo, JinYeong Bak, Kyunghyun Cho, Alice Oh

Dec 2022

HUE: Pretrained Model and Dataset for Understanding Hanja Documents of Ancient Korea

NAACL, Findings
HANEUL YOO, JIHO JIN, JUHEE SON, JINYEONG BAK, KYUNGHYUN CHO, ALICE OH

Jul 2022

Knowledge-Enhanced Evidence Retrieval for Counterargument Generation EMNLP, Findings

YOHAN JO, HANEUL YOO, JINYEONG BAK, ALICE OH, CHRIS REED, EDUARD HOVY

Nov 2021

Workshops and Posters

Exploring Student-ChatGPT Dialogue in EFL Writing Education

NeurIPS Workshop

JIEUN HAN*, **HANEUL YOO***, JUNHO MYUNG, MINSUN KIM, TAK YEON LEE, SO-YEON AHN, ALICE OH

Dec 2023

RECIPE: How to Integrate ChatGPT into EFL Writing Education

L@S, Work in Progress

Jieun Han*, **Haneul Yoo***, Yoonsu Kim, Junho Myung, Minsun Kim, Hyunseung Lim, Juho Kim, Tak Yeon Lee,
Hwajung Hong, So-Yeon Ahn, Alice Oh

Under Review / Preprints

Understanding the Role of Prompt Analytics Dashboard for EFL Writing Education with
Student-ChatGPT Interaction
under review

MINSUN KIM, JIEUN HAN, YOOSANG YOON, SEONGYEOM KIM, JUNHO MYUNG, **HANEUL YOO**, YOONSU KIM, HYUNSEUNG LIM, SOOYEON LEE, SO-YEON AHN, JUHO KIM, HWAJUNG HONG, ALICE OH, TAK YEON LEE

DRESS: Dataset for Rubric-based Essay Scoring on EFL Writing

HANEUL YOO. JIEUN HAN. SO-YEON AHN. ALICE OH

Feb 2024

Haneul Yoo, Jieun Han, So-Yeon Ahn, Alice Oh
Feb 2024

FABRIC: Automated Scoring and Feedback Generation for Essays preprint

JIEUN HAN*, **HANEUL YOO***, JUNHO MYUNG, MINSUN KIM, HYUNSEUNG LIM, YOONSU KIM, TAK YEON LEE, HWAJUNG HONG,
JUHO KIM, SO-YEON AHN, ALICE OH

Domestic Conferences / Journals

CLIcK: Evaluation of Cultural and Linguistic Intelligence in Korean

JKAIA

Juyoung Suk*, Eunsu Kim*, Philhoon Oh, **Haneul Yoo**, James Throne, Alice Oh

Image-based Deep Learning Approach for EEG Signal Classification

KICS

HANEUL YOO, JUNGRYUL SEO, KYUNG-AH SOHN Aug 2020

Proposal and Simulation of Optimal Electric Vehicle Routing Algorithm

KEPCO

Moonsuk Choi, Inji Choi, Minhae Jang, **Haneul Yoo**Mar 2020

Talks _____

Guest Lecturer Al Tech Boostcamp, "Several Aspects that We Should Consider about Data-Centric NLP" (May 2023)

Guest Lecturer Al Tech Boostcamp, "The Data You Constructed, Are You Sure It's Okay?" (Dec 2022)

Teaching Experiences _____

TA Al Tech Boostcamp (Spring 2023, Fall 2022) at NAVER Connect Foundation

Machine Learning for Natural Language Processing (Fall 2023), Al Ethics (Spring 2023), Al and Its Social Impact (Spring 2023), Machine Learning (Fall 2022, Spring 2021), KAIST SoC Colloquium (Fall 2021) at KAIST

Lecturer Python (Spring 2020) at Suwon Information Science High School, Java (Spring 2019) at Maetan High School

Academic Services _____

Program Committee ACL Workshop (2024)

Reviewer NeurIPS (2021, 2023), EMNLP (2022), ACL Rolling Review (2023 -)

Volunteer FAccT (2022), COLING (2022)

Honors and Awards _____

Academic Excellence Scholarship

KAIST Support Scholarship

Graduation with Honors

SUMMA CUM LAUDE (1ST PLACE)

Special Prize

KAIST Sep 2020 - Current

Sep 2020 - Current

Ajou University

Gyeonggi Volunteer Center

Aug 2020 er Center Jun 2020

Outstanding Volunteer Award Gyeonggi Voluntee

BIXPO

BIXPO 2019

Excellence Award

Nov 2019 KIPA

CREATIVE START-UP COMPETITION

Nov 2019 Asan Foundation

Mar 2017 - Aug 2020

References _____

Alice Oh Professor in School of Computing, KAIST